Guide to the Morris Edward Opler papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
Opler, Morris Edward papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
- Series VIII. Additional Uncategorised Material
  - FERG (Alan): Correspondence, Photos, etc. 1937-1991 (Box 122, Folder 25)
  - HEYE Foundation (Museum of the American Indian) 1987-1988 (Box 122, Folder 26)
  - IRONS (Correspondence, etc.) 1982-1984 (Box 122, Folder 27)
  - MANZANAR-Letters Prou ACLD and JACL, Inscriptions by Winin, (MEO File Drawer) Lucy Adams Letter, etc. 1943-1944 (Box 122, Folder 28)
  - OMORI, Emiko and Chizu (Files on Internment and Loyalty Question) 1993 (Box 122, Folder 29)
  - MATT MINES- Correspondence dictionary article on MEO (Box 122, Folder 30)
  - Perry, Edgar 1989 (Box 122, Folder 31)
  - NORMAN- Current Items 1985-1987 (Box 122, Folder 32)
  - Oklahoma and University of Oklahoma 1982-1985 (Box 122, Folder 33)
  - M.E.O.- Ideas 1947-1978 (Box 122, Folder 34)
  - M.E.O. Houors at O.U. (Authropology Award to Senstro and Native American Language Laboratory 1992 (Box 122, Folder 35)
  - PENDING 1984-1986 (Box 122, Folder 36)
  - APACHE Research Items: Pending on Library 1917-1980 (Box 122, Folder 37)
  - Peace River Films (Neil Goodwin) (Catalog) 1975 (Box 122, Folder 38)
  - Houser, Allan Sculpture of Navajo Shepherders on O.U. Campus (from Houser file) (LRO copy) 1995-1996 (Box 122, Folder 39)
  - Nostrand-Letter to MEO 1991 (Box 122, Folder 40)
  - MANZANAR- Letters from ACLU and JACL Inscriptions by Wiring Master Copies from Xeroxing (Also Lucy Adams letter) 1943-1944 (Box 122, Folder 41)
  - MANZANAR: Letters to MED from ACLU and JACL (Xerox copies) (Originals in File No.18-36) (Extras) 1943-1944 (Box 122, Folder 42)
  - MANZANAR-uscriptions in briefs written by MEO and JACL foreward (Extra Copies) 1944 (Box 122, Folder 43)
  - MANZANAR: Memo to MEO from Lucy Adams (Original in file No. 16-27) February 14, 1944 (Box 122, Folder 44)
  - Lipan Ethnography-typed copy (Box 122, Folder 45)
  - Lipan Ethnography-to be typed (Box 122, Folder 46)
  - Oklahoma Observer: M.E.O. Items 1981-1982 (Box 122, Folder 47)
  - MEO Bibliography-LRO copy, MEO biography-LRO copy 1907-1977 (Box 122, Folder 48)
  - Morris E. Opler Bibliography (numbered) Extra Copies 1935-1977 (Box 122, Folder 49)
  - Morris E. Opler Bibliography (not numbered) Exra Copies 1936-1977 (Box 122, Folder 50)
  - Extra Copies of B58 "Apache Religion" 1989-1990 (Box 122, Folder 51)
  - Extra Copies of B53 ("The Scott County Pueblo Site in Historical, Archaeological and Ethnological Perspective") 1982 (Box 122, Folder 52)
  - Extra Copies of Articles (MEO) 1987 (Box 122, Folder 53)
  - "The Apachean Culture Pattern and Its Origins," in Vol. 10, Southwest, ed. Alfonso Ortiz, of Handbook of North American Indians (gen. ed. William C. Sturtevant). Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, pp.368-392. (Synonymy by William J. de Reuse, pp.385-392) 1983 (Box 122, Folder 54)
  - "Chiricahua Apache," in Vol. 10, Southwest, ed. Alfonso Ortiz, of Handbook of North American Indians (gen. ed. William C. Sturtevant). Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, pp.401-418. (Synonymy by Ives Goddard, pp.416-418) 1983 (Box 122, Folder 55)
  - "Mescalero Apache," in Vol.10, Southwest, ed. Alfonso Ortiz, of Handbook of North American Indians (gen. ed. William C. Sturtevant). Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, pp.419-439. (Synonymy by Ives Goddard, pp.437-438) 1983 (Box 122, Folder 56)
  - "Foreword," in The Western Apache: Living with the Land Before 1950 by Winfred Buskirk. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, pp.xi-xii. 1986 (Box 122, Folder 57)
  - "Apache Religion," in The Encyclopedia of Religion, ed. Mircea Eliade et al. New York: Macmillan Publishing Co. 1987 (Box 122, Folder 58)
  - "Grenville Goodwin," in Western Apache Material Culture: The Goodwin and Guenther Collections, ed. Alan Ferg. Tucson: The University of Arizona Press (Published for the Arizona State Museum, The University of Arizona), pp.27-40 (Chapter 3). 1987 (Box 122, Folder 59)
  - "The Scott County Pueblo Site in Historical, Archaeological, and Ethnological Perspective," in Pathways to Plains Prehistory: Anthropological Perspectives of Plains Natives and Their Pasts. Papers in Honor of Robert E. Bell, eds. Don G. Wyckoff and Jack L. Hoffman. (Oklahoma Anthropological Society Memoir 3. The Cross Timbers Heritage Association Contributions 1). Duncan, Oklahoma: The Cross Timbers Press, pp.135-144. 1982 (Box 122, Folder 60)
  - The Lipan and Mescalero Apache in Texas. (Report Prepared for the Lipan-Mescalero Land Claims Case in October, 1970). New York and London: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1974. (Published, together with the report of Verne F. Ray, as Apache Indians X, in series autitled "American Indian Ethnohistory.") 1973-1974 (Box 123, Folder 1)
  - General Information RE MEO Materials (Key to bibliography system, filing system, serials lists, courses given, etc.) 1935-1967 (Box 123, Folder 2)
  - "The Concept of Supernatural Power among the Chiricahua and Mescalero Apaches," American Anthropologist, 37, No.1, 65-70. 1935 (Box 123, Folder 3)
  - "The Mescalero Apache Bow-Drill," American Anthropologist, 37, No.2, 370. 1935 (Box 123, Folder 4)
  - "A Note on the Cultural Affiliations of Northern Mexican Nomads," American Anthropologist, 37, No.4, 702-706. 1935 (Box 123, Folder 5)
  - "The Psychoanalytic Treatment of Culture," Psychoanalytic Review, XXII, No.2, 138-157. 1935 (Box 123, Folder 6)
  - "A Summary of Jicarilla Apache Culture," American Anthropologist, 38, No.2, 202-223. 1936 (Box 123, Folder 7)
  - "The Kinship Systems of the Southern Athabaskan-Speaking Tribes," American Anthropologist, 38, No.4, 620-633 1936 (Box 123, Folder 8)
  - "The Influence of Aboriginal Pattern and White Contact on a Recently Introduced Ceremony, the Mescalero Peyote Rite," Journal of American Folk-Lore, 49, Nos. 191-192, 143-166. 1936 (Box 123, Folder 9)
  - "An Interpretation of Ambivalence of Two American Indian Tribes," Journal of Social Psychology, 7 (1936), 82-116. Reprinted in Reader in Comparative Religion, eds. William Lesa and Evon Vogt. Evanston, Ill.: Row, Peterson and Co., 1958 pp.374-389. Also New York, Evanston and London: Harper and Row, Publishers, 1965 (2nd ed.), pp.421-432. 1936-1965 (Box 123, Folder 10)
  - "Some Points of Comparison and Contrast between the Treatment of Functional Disorders by Apache Shamans and Modern Psychiatric Practice," American Journal of Psychiatry, 92, No.6, 1371-1387. 1936 (Box 123, Folder 11)
  - "Apache Data Concerning the Relation of Kinship Terminology to Social Classification," American Anthropologist, 39, No.2, 201-212. 1937 (Box 123, Folder 12)
  - "A Chiricahua Apache's Account of the Geronimo Campaign of 1886," New Mexico Historical Review, No. 4, 360-386. 1938 (Box 123, Folder 13)
  - "Further Comparative Anthropological Data Bearing on the Solution of a Psychological Problem," Journal of Social Psychology, 9, 477-483. November, 1938 (Box 123, Folder 14)
  - "Humor and Wisdom of Some American Indian Tribes," New Mexico Anthropologist, III, No.1, 3-10. 1938 (Box 123, Folder 15)
  - "Personality and Culture: A Methodological Suggestion for the Study of their Interrelations," Psychiatry, I, No.2, 217-220. 1938 (Box 123, Folder 16)
  - "The Scared Clowns of the Chiricahua and Mescalero Indians," El Palacio, XLIV Nos. 10-12, 75-79. 1938 (Box 123, Folder 17)
  - "The Use of Peyote by the Carrizo and Lipan Apache Tribes," American Anthropologist, 40, No.2, 271-285. 1938 (Box 123, Folder 18)
  - "Anthropology, Democracy, and the School," California Journal of Elementary Education, VII, No.4, 206-209. 1939 (Box 123, Folder 19)
  - "A Description of a Tonkawa Peyote Meeting Held in 1902," American Anthroplogist, 41, No.3, 433-439. 1939 (Box 123, Folder 20)
  - "The Raid and War-Path Language of the Chiri. cahua Apache," (with Harry Hoijer), American Anthroplogist, 42, No.4, 617-634. 1940 (Box 123, Folder 21)
  - "A Jicarilla Apache Expedition and Scalp Dance," Journal of American Folklore, 54, Nos. 211-212, 10-23. 1941 (Box 123, Folder 22)
  - "Adolescence Rite of the Jicarilla," El Palacio, XLIX, No.2, 25-38. 1942 (Box 123, Folder 23)
  - "Examples of Ceremonial Interchanges among Southwestern Tribes," The Masterkey, XVI, No.3, 77-80. 1942 (Box 123, Folder 24)
  - "The Identity of the Apache Mansos," American Anthroplogist, 44, No.4, 725. 1942 (Box 123, Folder 25)
  - Review article of The Status System of a Modern Community by W. Lloyd Warner and Paul S. Lunt, in American Sociological Review, 7, No.5, 719-722. 1942 (Box 123, Folder 26)
  - "A Late Subscription," New Mexico Quarterly Review, XIII, No.1, 28-31. 1943 (Box 123, Folder 27)
  - "Navaho Shamanistic Practice among the Jicarilla Apache," New Mexico Anthroplogist, Vols. VI, VII, No.1, 13-18. 1943 (Box 123, Folder 28)
  - "On Method in the Writing of Anthropological Monographs," American Anthropologist, 45, No.2, 329-332. 1943 (Box 123, Folder 29)
  - "The Jicarilla Apache Ceremonial Relay Race," American Anthropologist, 46, No.1, 75-97. 1944 (Box 123, Folder 30)
  - "Cultural and Organic Conceptions in Contemporary World History," American Anthroplogist, 46, No.4, 448-460. 1944 (Box 123, Folder 31)
  - "Resistances to Resettlement," Proceedings of the Western Farm Economics Association, pp.266-271. 1944 (Box 123, Folder 32)
  - "Japanese Folk Belief Concerning the Snake," Southwestern Journal of Anthroplogy, I, No.2, 249-259. 1945 (Box 123, Folder 33)
  - "The Bio-Social Basis of Thought in the Third Reich," American Sociological Review, X, No.6, 776-786. 1945 (Box 123, Folder 34)
  - "Japanese Folk Belief Concerning the Cat," Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences, 35, No.9, 269-275 1945 (Box 123, Folder 35)
  - "A Mescalero Apache Account of the Origin of the Peyote Ceremony." El Palacio, LII, No.10, 210-212. 1945 (Box 123, Folder 36)
  - "Social Science and Democratic Policy," Applied Anthroplogy, 4, No.3, 11-15. 1945 (Box 123, Folder 37)
  - "Themes as Dynamic Forces in Culture," The American Journal of Sociology, LI, No.3, 198-206. (Reprint No. A-179 in the Bobbs-Merrill Reprint Series in the Social Sciences.) 1945 (Box 123, Folder 38)
  - "The Rice Goddess and the Fox in Japanese Religion and Folk Practice," (with Robert Seido Hashima), American Anthropologist, 48, No.1, 43-53. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 39)
  - "A Recent Trend in the Misrepresentation of the Work of American Ethnologists," American Anthropologist, 48, No.4, 669-671. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 40)
  - "The Use and Abuse of the Word 'Aryan'," El Palacio, LIII, No.1, 9-12. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 41)
  - "The Slaying of the Monsters, A Mescalero Apache Myth," El Palacio, LIII, No.8, 215-225 and No.9, 242-258. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 42)
  - "An Application of the Theory of Themes in Culture," Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences, 36, No.5, 137-166. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 43)
  - "Chiricahua Apache Material Relating to Sorcery," Primitive Man, XIX, Nos.3 and 4, 81-92. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 44)
  - "The Creative Role of Shamanism in Mescalero Apache Mythology," Journal of American Folklore, 59, No.233, 268-281. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 45)
  - "Mountain Spirits of the Chiricahua Apache," The Masterkey, XX, No.4,125-131. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 46)
  - "Psychiatry and Applied Anthropology in Psychological Warfare against Japan," (with Alexander H. Leighton), The American Journal of Psychoanalysis, VI, No.1, 20-27. Reprinted in The Process and Effects of Mass Communication, ed. Wilbur Schramm. Urbana, Ill.: University of Illinois Press, pp.157-169. Also reprinted in part under title, "Psychological Warfare and the Japanese Eurperor," in Personalities and Cultures: Readings in Psychological Authroplogy, ed. Robert Hunt. Gardeu City, N.Y.: The Natural History Press (for the American Museum of Natural History), pp.251-260. 1967 (Box 123, Folder 47)
  - "Reaction to Death among the Mescalero Apache," Southwestern Journal of Anthropology 2, No.4, 454-467. 1946 (Box 123, Folder 48)
  - "Rejoinder," The American Journal of Sociology, LII, No.1, 43-44. (Rejoinder to Albert K. Cohen's comment.) 1946 (Box 123, Folder 49)
  - "Cultural Alternatives and Educational Theory," Harvard Educational Review, 12, No.1, 28-44. 1947 (Box 123, Folder 50)
  - "The Use of the Political-Behavior Approach in Civic Education," (with William O. Penrose), Harvard Educational Review, 17, No.4, 242-253. 1947 (Box 123, Folder 51)
  - "Fact and Fallacy Concerning the Evolution of Man," Philosophy and Phenomenological Research, VII, No.4, 635-642. 1947 (Box 123, Folder 52)
  - "Mythology and Folk Belief in the Maintenance of Jicarilla Apache Tribal Endogamy," Journal of American Folklore, 60, No.236, 126-129. 1947 (Box 123, Folder 53)
  - "Notes on Chiricahua Apache Culture. 1.Supernatural Power and the Shaman," Primitive Man, 20, Nos. 1 and 2, 1-14. 1947 (Box 123, Folder 54)
  - "Rule and Practice in the Behavior Between Jicarilla Apache Affinal Relatives," American Anthropologist, 49, No.3, 453-462. 1947 (Box 123, Folder 55)
  - "Theories of Culture and the Deviant," An Educational Philosophy for Exceptional Children: Proceedings of the Spring Conference on Education and the Exceptional Child of the Child Research Clinic of The Woods Schools, Langhorne, Pa., pp.8-14. May, 1947 (Box 123, Folder 56)
  - "Jicarilla Apache Fertility Aids, and Practices for Preventing Conception," American Anthropologist, 50, No.2, 359-361. 1948 (Box 123, Folder 57)
  - "A Redefinition of Prejudice for Purposes of Social Science Research," (with William E. Vickery), Human Relations, 1, No.4, 419-428. 1948 (Box 123, Folder 58)
  - "Some Implications of Culture Theory for Anthropology and Psychology," The American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, XVIII, No.4, 611-621. 1948 (Box 123, Folder 59)
  - "Some Recently Developed Concepts Relating to Culture," Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 4, No.2, 107-122. 1948 (Box 123, Folder 60)
  - "The Context of Themes," American Anthropologist, 51, No.2, 323-325. 1949 (Box 123, Folder 61)
  - "Words Without Meaning or Culture," Word (Journal of the Linguistic Circle of New York), 5, No.1, 42-44. April, 1949 (Box 123, Folder 62)
  - "The Tasks before Free India," The Delphian Quarterly, 33, No.3, 6-9. 1950 (Box 123, Folder 63)
  - "India Plans Her Rural Economy," The Delpian Quarterly, 33, No.4, 4-7, 21. 1950 (Box 123, Folder 64)
  - "Mescalero Apache History in the Southwest," (with Catherine H. Opler), New Mexico Historical Review, XXV, No.1, 1-36. 1950 (Box 123, Folder 65)
  - "The Changing Status of Women in India," The Delphian Quarterly, 34, No. 2, 6-8, 21. 1951 (Box 123, Folder 66)
  - "The Chinese Family under Communism," The Delphian Quarterly, 34, No.4, 1-4. 1951 (Box 123, Folder 67)
  - "Economic, Political and Social Change in a Village of North Central India," (with Rudra Datt Singh), Human Organization, ll, No.2, 5-12. 1952 (Box 123, Folder 68)
  - "Kashmir: Past Events and Future Prospects," The Delphian Quarterly, 35, No.3, 9-13. 1952 (Box 123, Folder 69)
  - "North American Indians," Encyclopdia of the Tamil Academy, Madras, India. 1952 (Box 123, Folder 70)
  - "Two Villages of Eastern Uttar Pradesh (U.P.), India: An Analysis of Similarities and Differences," (with Rudra Datt Singh), American Anthropologist, 54, No.2, 179-190. 1952 (Box 123, Folder 71)
  - "Problems Concerning Official and Popular Participation in Development and Cultural Change, II. No.4, 269-278. 1954 (Box 123, Folder 72)
  - "Some Recent Ethnographic Work in India," Bulletin of the Philadelphia Anthroplogical Society, 8, No.3, 4-5. May, 1955 (Box 123, Folder 73)
  - Review article of Village India: Studies in the Little Community, ed. McKim Marriott, Far Eastern Quarterly, 26, 146-153. November, 1955 (Box 123, Folder 74)
  - "The Extensions of an Indian Village," The Journal of Asian Studies, XVI, No.1, 5-10. Reprinted in Peasant Society: A Reader, eds. Jack M. Potter, May N. Diaz, and George M. Foster, Bosten: Little, Brown and Company, pp.42-47. Also reprinted in Articles and Excerpts to Accompany the Civilization of India Syllabus, Vol.I, ed. Joseph W. Elder (with the assistance of Willard L. Johnson and Christopher L. King). Madison, Wis: Dept. of Indian Studies, U. of Wisconsin, pp.2-4. 1956, 1966 and 1967 (Box 123, Folder 75)
  - "Indian National and State Elections in a Village Context," (with William L. Rowe and Mildred L. Stroop), Human Organization, 18, No.1, 30-34. Reprinted in Studies in Indian Democracy, ed. S.P. Aiyar and R. Srinavasan, Bowbay, New Delhi, Calcutta, Madras, London and New York: ALlied Publishers Private, Ltd.), pp. 641-653. 1965 (Box 123, Folder 76)
  - "Elsie Clews Parsons," Encyclopaedia Britannica, Chicago, Illinois. (Article written in 1959.) 1959 (Box 123, Folder 77)
  - "Apache," Encyclopaedia Britannica, Chicago, Illinois. (Article written in 1959.) 1959 (Box 123, Folder 78)
  - "New Approaches to North American Indian Traditions;" Journal of American Folklore, 72, No.284, 95-96. 1959 (Box 123, Folder 79)
  - "Technological Change and Social Organization in a Village of North India," Anthropological Quarterly, 32, No.3, 127-133. Reprinted in condensed form in Selected Abstracts in Development Administration: Field Reports of Directed Social Change, eds. Donn V. Hart and Paul Meadows. (Publication No.3, Maxwell Graduate School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University.) January, 1962 (Box 123, Folder 80)
  - "Jicarilla Apache Fertility Aids, and Practices for Preventing Conception," American Anthropologist, 50, No.2, 359-361. 1948 (Box 123, Folder 81)
  - "The Place of Religion in a North Indian Village," Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 15, No.3, 219-226. 1959 (Box 123, Folder 82)
  - "Component, Assemblage, and Theme in Cultural Integration and Differentiation," American Anthropologist, 61, No. 6, 955-964. 1959 (Box 123, Folder 83)
  - "Considerations in the Cross-Cultural Study of Mental Disorders," The International Journal of Social Psychiatry, V, No.3, 191-196. 1959 (Box 123, Folder 84)
  - "Recent Changes in Family Structure in an Indian Village," Anthropological Quarterly, 33, No.2, 93-97. 1960 (Box 123, Folder 85)
  - "The Hijara (Hermaphrodites) of India and Indian National Character: A Rejoinder," American Anthropologist, 62, No.3, 505-511. 1960 (Box 123, Folder 86)
  - "Myth and Practice in Jicarilla Apache Eschatology," Journal of American Folklore, 73, 288, 133-153. 1960 (Box 123, Folder 87)
  - "Political Organization and Economic Growth--The Case of Village India," International Review of Community Development, No.5, 187-197. (Summary in Italian on pp. 199-201.) (This issue deals with and is entitled "Theories and Values.") 1960 (Box 123, Folder 88)
  - "Cultures and Customs Throughout History," New York Herald Tribune, (Review article on paperbacks in archaeology and anthropology.) January 15, 1961 (Box 123, Folder 89)
  - Articles on "Brahman", "Caste", "Kshatriya", "Sudra", and "Vaishya" in The Grolier Encyclopedia, New York, N.Y. (Written in 1961) 1961 (Box 123, Folder 90)
  - "Cultural Evolution, Southern Athapaskans, and Chronology in Theory," Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 17, No.1, 1-20. 1961 (Box 123, Folder 91)
  - "Further Comparative Notes on the Hijara of India," American Anthropologist, 63, No.6, 1331-1332. 1961 (Box 123, Folder 92)
  - "The Death Practices and Eschatology of the Kiowa Apache," (with William E. Bittle), Southwestern Journal of Anthrophology, 17, No.4, 383-394. 1961 (Box 123, Folder 93)
  - "Two Converging Lines of Influence in Cultural Evolutionary Theory," American Anthropologist, 64, No.3, Pt.1, 524-547. 1962 (Box 123, Folder 94)
  - "Integration, Evolution, and Morgan," Current Anthropology, 3, No.5, 478-479. 1962 (Box 123, Folder 95)
  - "The Cultural Definition of Illness in Village India," Human Organization, 22, No.1, 32-35. 1963 (Box 123, Folder 96)
  - "Testing and Evolutionary Theory," Human Organization, 22, No.2, 159-162. 1963 (Box 123, Folder 97)
  - "Cultural Anthropology: An Addendum to a 'Working Paper," American Anthropologist, 65, No.4, 897-903. 1963 (Box 123, Folder 98)
  - "Reflections on the Downgrading of Man and the Grading of Cultures: A Reply," American Anthroplogist, 66, No.2, 401-404. 1964 (Box 123, Folder 99)
  - "Morgan and Materialism: A Reply to Thomas G. Harding and Eleanor Leacock," Current Anthropology, 5, No.2, 110-114. 1964 (Box 123, Folder 100)
  - "Particularization and Generalization as Processes in Ritual and Culturre," Journal of Asian Studies, XXIII, 83-87 (special issue). Also appears as article in book entitled Religion in South Asia, ed. Edward B. Harper (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1964), pp.83-87. June, 1964 (Box 123, Folder 101)
  - "The Human Being in Culture Theory," American Anthropologist, 66, No.3, 507-528. Reprinted in Readings in Anthroplogy. Vol.II, Cultural Anthropology, ed. Morton H. Fried. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell Company, (2nd ed.), pp.19-42. 1964 and 1968 (Box 123, Folder 102)
  - "The Lipan Apache Death Complex and Its Extensions," Southwestern Journal of Anthroplogy, I, No.1, 122-141. 1945 (Box 123, Folder 103)
  - M.E.O.-Festschrift #2 and Dinner at AAA Meetings (Houston 12/1/77) 1976-1978 (Box 123, Folder 104)
  - An Apache Life-Way-Republication 1965-1971 (Box 123, Folder 105)
  - Larry Kelly Interviews of M.R.O. and Correspondence (File with M.E.O. Biographical Morris) 1976-1980 (Box 124, Folder 1)
  - M.E.O.-Festschrift #1 1972-1977 (Box 124, Folder 2)
  - "Cause, Process, and Dynamics in the Evolutionism of E.B. Tylor," Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 20, No.2, 123-144. 1964 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - "The History of Ethnological Thought," in the Discussion and Criticism section of Current Anthropology, 6, No.3, 319-320. 1965 (Box 124, Folder 4)
  - "Comment on Theodore Brameld," Human Organization, 24, No.4, 295. 1965 (Box 124, Folder 5)
  - "More on the History of Ethnological Thought," in the Discussion and Criticism section of Current Anthropology, 7, No.3, 355. 1966 (Box 124, Folder 6)
  - Article on "Apache Indians" in The American Peoples Encyclopedia, New York, N.Y. (Article written in 1966.) 1966 (Box 124, Folder 7)
  - Article on "Themes of Culture" ("Kulturthemen"), in Worterbuch der Soziologie, ed. Wilhelm Bernsdorf. Stuttgart: Ferdinand Enke. (Written in 1967: published in 1969.) Pages 609-611. 1967 and 1969 (Box 124, Folder 8)
  - "Franz Boas: Religion and Theory," in the Letters to the Editor section, American Anthropologist, 69, No.6, 741-745. 1967 (Box 124, Folder 9)
  - "Tylor's Application of Evolutionary Theory to Public Issues of His Day," Anthropological Quarterly, 41, No.1, 1-8. 1968 (Box 124, Folder 10)
  - "Remuneration to Supernaturals and Man in Apachean Ceremonialism," Ethnology, 7, No.4, 356-393. 1968 (Box 124, Folder 11)
  - "The Themal Approach in Cultural Anthroplogy and Its Application to North Indian Data," Southwestern Journal of Anthroplogy, 24, No.3, 215-227. 1968 (Box 124, Folder 12)
  - "Palanquin Symbolism: The Special Vocabulary of the Palanquin-bearing Castes of North Central India," (with Shaligram Shukla), Journal of American Folklore, 81, No.321, 216-234. 1968 (Box 124, Folder 13)
  - "Cultural Relativity, Modern Research, and Melville Herskovits," American Anthroplogist, 70, No.3, 563-564. 1968 (Box 124, Folder 14)
  - "Western Apache and Kiowa Apache Materials Relating to Ceremonial Payment," Ethnology, 8, No.1, 122-124. 1969 (Box 124, Folder 15)
  - "The Son and Daughter in Eastern Uttar Pradesh Proverbs and Sayings," (with Shaligram Shukla), The Anthroplogist (University of Delhi), Special Volume II, pp.15-21. (Issued in 1969). 1968-1969 (Box 124, Folder 16)
  - "Jicarilla Apache Territory, Economy, and Society in 1850," Southwestern Journal of Anthroplogy, 27, No.4, 309-329. 1971 (Box 124, Folder 17)